So I'm here
today to talk about a project of mine
that I've been working on
for a little while.
It is a small standalone device that,
the generates poems in the Alba Chandra.
Sorry, I'm getting.
Zoom is putting all kinds of things
on my screen that I'm trying to deal with.
So that is also known as obeyed
or to any number of other names
in different cultures.
It's actually a remarkably universal
form of poetry.
So the device that I'm using generates
poetry using an extremely small language
model, a Markov chain,
which is technically a language model
that is entirely trained on a corpus
of all this that I gathered and curated
and annotated by hand.
If you haven't seen an Alba before,
this is an example from From My Purpose.
This is an Irish folk song, actually,
just one verse from it,
but it kind of demonstrates
the themes on a mossy bank.
I sat me down with the maiden by my side.
With gentle words.
I poured her and asked her for my bride.
She said, young man, don't bring me blame.
But let me go away from warning.
Morning's light is shining bright
by the dawning of the day.
So you have these two lovers.
Sun shows up, spoils
their fun knots and all that.
This is
the current iteration of the device.
I have it right here.
Also,
if you want to get an idea of the scale,
there's a small screen in the bottom right
corner, a small solar panel to the left,
and then some big capacitors on the upper
right hand side there.
So mostly what I'm going to talk about
today is some
technical specifics that I want to that
I want to go through and talk about
some of the things that I've learned
while making this project.
So broadly, my goals
with this project.
Trying to see.
Just not actually advancing.
Broadly, my goals with this project
are to.
Think about basically how much energy
it actually takes to generate
non-trivial creative text.
And in that, in that area,
I'm building on a lot of existing work in
electronic literature,
in constrained text generation.
Lots of Nick Montfort's work,
for example, PPG 256 and then the stuff
that's being currently published
by the publication taper.
So I'm trying to think like what?
What is the smallest, least energy
intensive, non-trivial poetry generator?
And you can create all these expensive.
I also feel like as a culture,
we've been engaging
over the past few years
in a very large scale research project
on the affordances of language models.
With results that range, in my opinion,
from from boring to catastrophically bad.
Most of that data, most of that research
projects been happening
on, like the the big language models.
And I kind of feel
like we have a pretty good idea
of what's happening, of what
those big language models do.
But I still think there's stuff
to learn from smaller language
models, small Markov chain, small corpora
that we've really paid
attention to and, and things like that.
So this also seems like a good opportunity
to gather further evidence
about how the materiality of a system
for generating poetic texts
actually affects the received.
So what are the actual expressive
affordances available
when when poets are making
these really low level decisions
about the hardware
that the generators are running on?
And then of course, I'm just interested
in the all the, in general.
And there's sort of like this
obvious synergy between all those
and the and the project of making solar
powered poetry generator
because they're both about the sun.
And I'm going to talk more
about that later.
All right.
So these are a couple of previous
prototypes of the device I've,
over the past couple of years
actually have switched processors.
I've switched output types.
I've made my own PCB.
This one over here
is the first one that I tried out.
The main thing that's new in the version
that I'm showing today is the ink screen,
and also the real time clock chip,
which I'll talk about one second.
So the physical components of the device,
I'm just saying this is the
this is the back of the device
where all of the electronics are just
to kind of give you an idea of what,
what components are
and what's happening there.
First
there is the Raspberry Pi Pico 2040
right here.
That's the microcontroller.
It's the kind of the brains
of the of the system.
That's where the code runs.
It has an associated flash chip that has
both the code and the purpose on it.
The 2040 has about 256kB of Ram,
which is not a lot,
but I managed to make my Markov model fit.
There's also a small screen
which is on the previous screen,
but then there's all this
support electronics that go along with
that to deliver the right power.
And then there's a real time clock
I see here.
Computers, of course,
don't know about the passage of time
unless you tell them about it.
And artsy Chip actually keeps running
even when the rest of
the device is powered down.
It uses
this battery as a backup
and this supercapacitor as a backup,
so that when the device opens up
the next time,
it will remember what the current date
and time is.
And then there's this solar harvester
I see.
And we'll talk about that in the context
of how the device works
as a whole. So.
The way that it works is
there is the sun, as you know,
big bright sphere in the sky
hits the solar panel, small solar panel.
And then the energy from the solar panel
goes to that solar harvester IC.
So keeping track of exactly
when and how to let energy
from the solar panel into
the rest of the system is pretty tricky.
And that's what the harvester
IC takes care of.
So it gradually fills up
the supercapacitors.
These little guys right here,
until there's
enough energy stored up that it can safely
start the microcontroller.
The microcontroller
needs like a steady 3.3V.
And without that, it's
just not going to function very well.
When that's detected.
The harvester I see discharges
the capacitors into the microcontroller.
Among the microcontroller runs its code.
In this case it's the code to generate
the poem and put it on to the display.
The amount of power
that we're talking about here is,
is comparatively very small.
It's about 80 milliamps at 3.3V.
And that lasts for 30
or 40s for reference.
That's like less than the amount of power
that most laptop
computers used
when they're when they're in sleep mode.
So all of this is happening
with like less energy
than your computer is using
when it's not doing anything.
And then when the supercapacitors
are depleted, the harvester shuts down,
should send the microcontroller cleanly.
The great thing about the display,
of course, is that
once you've updated it, it sticks,
unlike other kinds of displays
that required to constantly refresh it,
the display will retain its contents
even when no power is being applied,
so it makes it ideal for this purpose.
And there's also a little serial interface
that I wrote.
So if you connect to the device over USB,
their little commands that you can type in
to do things like change the change
the date that it thinks that it is,
generate a poem, get other status
information from the device.
So here's a little video
of what it looks like
when the device is updating.
Just kind of that classic.
Let me blank everything out
and then replace it with something else.
The software side of this,
if I can get,
there are a couple of components
to the software.
Nothing.
I'm going into the software in detail
would be a little different talk, but
there are drivers for the display
and the real time clock
I see, which I decided
to re-implement from scratch.
There are libraries out there,
but they didn't quite work
the way that I wanted to.
And then there's the language
model code itself,
and I'm using the term
language model in its broadest sense here,
meaning like a statistical model
that gives you the probability
of a particular token occurring in a text
given some context.
The language model in
this case is not a very sophisticated
language model.
It's just a Markov model,
which is the kind of thing,
probably the only kind of language model
that you can make
in this kind of constrained environment.
My notes won't scroll outside, and
I did write everything myself in C,
which was kind of an adventure for me.
Probably the biggest thing
that I've written in C is like a project,
but the project kind of demands that
because it is really close
to the hardware, and if I want to actually
squeeze these last little bits of energy
out of every charge,
you kind of need to write in a language
that allows you to do that.
The corpus
to explain a little bit about that,
they are the corpus is what it uses
to build the Markov model.
So it's the data set for the generator.
It consists
entirely of poems in the Alba.
And sometimes I kind of had to broadly
construe that, that are in English
that are also available
in the public domain.
And all of those vectors are there
to make sure that I'm working with text
that I can, that I'm actually authorized
to reuse text, that I can attribute,
text that I can redistribute
and build upon without in a way
that actually builds
the commons instead of extracts from it.
That English public domain constraint
is kind of a problem
because English, it turns out,
does not have
a strong tradition of the alba or robot.
Or minutes two minutes.
So no.
So a lot of
the poems in that, that we might think
of, like the troubadours and stuff
like that, there aren't good public
domain translations of those.
So what I end up with
this is the the number of texts
that are in the corpus.
A lot of these I just copied
and pasted from Project Gutenberg.
Others I had to like, go fishing
through different bibliographies about
all the zero bods in order to track down
these poems in books
that have been digitized
but haven't yet been transcribed.
This is what a typical entry in the corpus
looks like.
I will entry
a little bit of text at the top
that explains where the text came from.
Has a bibliographic citation.
I also did some hand tagging of the text,
which I'm not going to be able
to talk about today, but that I use
during the text generation process.
So just really quickly to
the last thing that I
want to talk about here is.
Kind of
what I learned about Albas
by making this the choice of all business.
The corpus for this project is always kind
of seemed intuitively correct,
but I've been struggling
to really figure out why that's the case.
There's a certain irony and cuteness
to having a solar powered device
that produces poems
about how the sun sucks,
but I don't think that is the end
of the complexity of the relationship.
So is when I was working on
actually the real time.
When I was working on the real time
clock code for this,
I went back to
The Sun Rising, which is by by John Donne.
It's kind of like
I think the the most commonly known
obeyed in the English poetic tradition.
And that poem begins physical, full,
unruly sun.
Thus, through windows
and through curtains, calling us love.
All like no season knows, nor climb,
nor hours, days, months.
Which are the rags of time.
To get
to my actual notes and not happening.
And so the thing that sticks out here is
all those aren't just about lovers
and the drama of young lovers.
I'm almost done.
Sorry.
They're also kind of about grief.
What?
What's happening here
is that this timelessness
of being together
is interrupted by the sun,
which is like the stand in
for the concept of time in general.
And.
So then the sun shows up.
It's dressed in its rags of time,
the clock starts up again, and suddenly
that state of infinite possibility
has to resolve into just a single outcome.
So the application of the sun's energy
resolves love's meta stability.
And lovers experience that as grief.
And I think there's an analogy there
for this kind
of a weird comparison
for electronic devices like before.
This is powered.
It has all of its potential,
like a seed inside
of it, and that potential only unwinds
when power
is applied to it, and then suddenly
it's not potential anymore.
It has to resolve to this one
particular output.
So that's that's kind of the
the similarity between these things.
That's driving me forward.
As I continue to work on this project.
There is a GitHub or not GitHub, a git
repository IRL.
I haven't put anything up there yet,
but I do plan on putting all of the source
code,
the design files and so forth online.
If not today,
then in the next couple of days.
So that's it. Thank you.